Guide to the Tough Club Records 1906-1997 MS 3217
New-York Historical Society
Tough Club records
1906-1997
New-York Historical Society
Tough Club (New York)
MS 3217
2.5 Linear feet in 3 boxes.
A small collection of the surviving, spotty records of the Tough Club, a males-only fraternal and mutual aid society founded in Greenwich Village in 1865 "to inculcate loyal friendship, goodwill and social congeniality among its members" through frequent gatherings and by maintaining a benevolent fund. The membership attracted men from various trades and businesses, as well as civic leaders and politicians, among them New York City mayors Jimmy Walker and Fiorello La Guardia. From 1912 until its dissolution in 1996-1997, the Tough Club operated from its headquarters at 243 West 14th Street. The collection includes prospective membership cards, organizational files, some financial records, and several objects, most notably a cudgel or shillelagh, a wooden club originally associated with Irish folklore, which possibly served a ceremonial function at Tough Club meetings.
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored offsite. For information on making arrangements to consult it, please see www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
The cassette tapes in Series IV are restricted in order to preserve them and because the New-York Historical Society lacks the necessary playback equipment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Patricia Dunlavy Valenti and Peter L. Valenti, 2022.
Arrangement
The Tough Club Records are organized in five series:
Series I.
Tough Club membership cards, 1906-[1993]
Series II.
Tough Club organizational files, 1910-1997
Series III.
Tough Club financial records, 1980-1993
Series IV.
Tough Club audio cassettes, 1992-199[4], undated
Series V.
Tough Club objects, [19th-20th century]
Historical note
Several likely apocryphal stories survive to explain the origins of the name of the Tough Club. In one, the group—which was organized on November 10, 1865—was first called the "Topf Club" because it met in a billiard room and café run by George Topf at the corner of Hudson and West 10th Streets in Greenwich Village. ("Trow's New York City Directory... For the Year Ending May 1, 1865," lists a man by that name, whose business was "beer" at 145 [now 247] West 10th Street and who lived at 512 Hudson Street.) Another has it that the organization took its name from the German word for cooking pot, "topf," a nod to the giant cauldron the club owned and used to make chowder for its functions well into the twentieth century. (Pictured in the New York Times on October 15, 1960, the cauldron was variously described as holding between fifty and 120 gallons.) While one account places the switch from "Topf" to "Tough" a few months after the club's founding, another says that in 1873 a printer mistakenly produced thousands of sheets of stationery with the club name spelled "Tough" instead of "Topf." Rather than redo the order, the club simply adopted the wrong name, under which it was incorporated on June 29, 1896. (Some online sources refer to the organization as the "Tammany Tough Club," a name by which it was never known.)
The objects of the males-only Tough Club (wives were called "Toughettes"), as laid out in its by-laws, were "to inculcate loyal friendship, goodwill and social congeniality among its members; to promote their welfare, happiness and good fellowship; to provide, advance and maintain social and recreative entertainment for their welfare and enjoyment; to aid, succor and befriend the members of the Club in the time of need and distress; to maintain funds for the purpose of aiding, befriending and assisting the members of this Club in any manner deemed advisable, and to provide, keep and maintain a Benevolent or Mortuary Fund, for those who wish to participate." The club's motto—"Bend but never break"—was more in line with toughness than with chowder pots, but food and general merry-making seemed high priorities for the Brother Toughs (as they dubbed themselves), whose "outings, beefsteaks, clambakes, chowder parties, stag hunts, balls and get-togethers" filled the social calendar.
Membership was limited to 500, and over the years attracted notables from varied fields, like boxer Gene Tunney and entertainer George M. Cohan. Although its rules prohibited partisan politics, the Tough Club counted as members New York's Governor Al Smith and several New York City mayors, among them Jimmy Walker, Fiorello La Guardia, and Robert F. Wagner Jr. The New York Times reported on February 15, 1962 that Mayor Wagner was examining the policies of clubs to which he belonged, and expected to quit any that discriminated. In response, the Tough Club noted their "lack of Negro members and applicants, but said they had no restrictive policies." That statement diverged from the club's published by-laws, which offered membership to "any white male person" who was "a citizen of the United States, of good moral character and repute, whose health [was] in good condition, over the age of twenty-one (21) years." (In 1993 a proposed revision of the by-laws eliminated the phrase "white male," but it is unknown if the change was adopted. See Box 2, Folder 15.)
The Tough Club had several headquarters in its early decades before settling in its own meeting rooms at 80 Bedford Street. On February 1, 1893 it moved to 27 Grove Street, where it remained until November 8, 1912. On that date the club first occupied its final home, a four-story rowhouse at 243 West 14th Street, which it had purchased the previous year. In 1986, after more than seven decades, the club sold the building in an effort to increase capital. It retained a 99-year lease for the ground floor and basement at $1.00 per year, but a general fading of interest among its dwindling membership led the Tough Club to dissolve and distribute its assets in 1996-1997.
[This note is based largely on Tough Club histories (Box 2, Folder 4), its constitution and by-laws (Box 2, Folder 6), and other documents in the present collection.]
Scope and Contents
This collection preserves the surviving, though spotty records of the Tough Club, beginning in 1906, four decades after its founding, and running to 1997, when it folded after more than 130 years of existence. There are large gaps in coverage spread among different formats: organizational files (mostly from the 1980s and 1990s and containing a mix of correspondence, financial reports, and meeting minutes, but also holding the original deed to the club's headquarters at 243 West 14th Street); account books (recording membership dues of the 1980s), audio cassettes (apparently capturing a handful of meetings from the early 1990s), and objects (such as the club's corporate seal embosser). The most substantial, and, perhaps, significant portion of the collection is its proposition for membership cards, which span 1906-1926, and record the name, age, address, and occupation of each applicant, and the date of his admittance to the club.
Clubs -- New York (State) -- New York.; Fraternal organizations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Private clubs -- New York (State) -- New York.; Account books.; Audiocassettes.; Bank statements.; Bylaws (administrative records); Correspondence.; Embossers.; Financial statements.; Membership cards.; Minutes (administrative records); Receipts (financial records); Rubber stamps.; Shillelaghs.; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.
- Series I. Tough Club membership cards, 1906-[1993]
  - Tough Club proposition for membership cards (filed alphabetically), 1906-1926 (Offsite-box 1, Enclosure A (section 1))
    Scope and Contents
    Cards record prospective members, their address, occupation, age, and which member proposed them. Cards are preprinted forms, with the Tough Club's addresses of 27 Grove Street (before November 8, 1912) and 243 West 14th Street (after November 8, 1912). Some earlier cards are of a larger format, with a "Medical Examiner's Blank" on the verso, recording the results of a prospective member's medical exam and physical fitness for club activities and insurance policies.
  - Tough Club membership index cards (filed alphabetically), 1974-1982, undated (Offsite-box 1, Enclosure A (section 2))
    Handwritten or typed index cards recording name, address, and for some members, date joined, date dues paid, whether or not membership is active, whether member is deceased.
  - Tough Club officer and board member index cards (filed alphabetically), [circa 1993] (Offsite-box 1, Enclosure A (section 3))
- Series II. Tough Club organizational files, 1910-1997
  - Abstract of title [243 West 14th Street, Manhattan], [1910 March 10] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    "Abstract of the title of Charles C. Bailey to premises shown on the following diagram."
  - Deed [243 West 14th Street, Manhattan], 1911 January 10 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    Charles C. Bailey to The Tough Club. Original deed plus photocopy.
  - Treasurer's bond, [1911] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    Fidelity and Casualty Company of New York. Individual Standard Fidelity Bond. Employer: Tough Club. Employee: Otto H. Wenderoth.
  - Histories of the Tough Club, [1925, circa 1965] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    Contains "History of the Tough Club, 1865-1925" (1925), and "Background Information from the Tough Club" (circa 1965).
  - Tough Club activities, 1931-1993, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    Original folder labeled "Documents pertaining to social events, lyrics [and music] to 'A Brother Tough,' etc." "A Brother Tough," the club's song, was written by member Jules Soubiran to lyrics by Alice Weber.
  - Constitution and By-Laws of the Tough Club... Revised October 13th, 1952 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jack Newfield, "The Ten Worst Judges in New York," New York Magazine, 1972 October 16 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes a profile of longtime Tough Club president Judge Gerald Culkin (1906-1993).
  - Tough Club files (taxes), 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Tough Club files (financial report), 1985 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - Tough Club files (correspondence, petition, sale of club building), 1986 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Tough Club files (correspondence, financial reports, taxes), 1987 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - Tough Club files (correspondence, financial reports), 1988-1989 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - Tough Club files (correspondence, financial reports), 1990 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
  - Tough Club files (correspondence, meeting minutes, receipts), 1991 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
  - Tough Club files (correspondence, financial reports, meeting minutes), 1992-1993 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
  - Tough Club files (correspondence, meeting minutes, receipts), 1994 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
  - Tough Club files (correspondence, petition for dissolution), 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
  - Tough Club files (correspondence, agreement), 1996 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Tough Club files (correspondence, notes), 1997 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  - Tough Club stationery (blank letterhead, receipts, and envelopes), undated [after 1963] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
- Series III. Tough Club financial records, 1980-1993
  - Tough Club account book (membership dues), 1980-1985 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Tough Club account book (membership dues, finances), 1985-1986 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Tough Club account book (membership dues), 1987-1989 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Tough Club bank statements, 1985-1986 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - Tough Club deposit receipts (membership dues), 1992-1993 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
- Series IV. Tough Club audio cassettes, 1992-199[4], undated
  Restricted
  The cassette tapes in Series IV are restricted in order to preserve them and because the New-York Historical Society lacks the necessary playback equipment.
  - Tough Club meeting, [1992? 1994?] March 2 (Offsite-box 1, Enclosure B)
  - Tough Club meeting, 1993 November 8 (Offsite-box 1, Enclosure B)
  - Tough Club meeting, 1993 December 6 (Offsite-box 1, Enclosure B)
  - Tough Club meeting, undated (Offsite-box 1, Enclosure B)
  - LINCOLN by Philip B. Kunhardt, Jr., Peter W. Kunhardt, and Philip B. Kunhardt III, read by Frank Langella, 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Enclosure B)
  - Unlabeled [8 cassettes], undated (Offsite-box 1, Enclosure B)
    It is unknown whether these tapes are blank or hold recordings.
- Series V. Tough Club objects, [19th-20th century]
  - Tough Club shillelagh or cudgel, [19th century?] (Offsite-box 3)
    A cudgel or shillelagh (a wooden club associated with Irish folklore), possibly of oak, carved on its knob with an image of a building resembling a church. Its handle is drilled through with a wire for hanging. That, and the overall dark (almost black) color of the wood suggests it was displayed for a long time, likely in the Tough Club's barroom. It is unclear if this object served a ceremonial purpose at club meetings. It is not mentioned in the organization's constitution and by-laws (Box 2, Folder 6), or written histories (Box 2, Folders 2 and 4), and the Tough Club's mission was not officially or explicitly Irish in focus. (That said, the Toughs hosted an "Irish Night" on St. Patrick's Day, 1993. See Box 2, Folder 5.) Perhaps the shillelagh was donated by a member and kept for its symbolism, i.e., a "tough club," as in a "sturdy stick," for the Tough Club.
  - Tough Club corporate seal embosser, [19th-20th century] (Offsite-box 1, Enclosure C)
    Produces a monogram of the entwined letters "TC" (for "Tough Club") encircled by the legend "TOUGH CLUB ORGANIZED NOV. 10, 1865."
  - Tough Club return address rubber stamp, [after 1963] (Offsite-box 1, Enclosure C)
    Reads "The Tough Club Inc. / 243 W. 14th St. / New York, N.Y. 10011"